<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A true copy of a speech made by an English colonel to his regiment, immediately before their late transportation for Flanders at Harwich</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1691</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 39 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 7 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A95011</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing T2633A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R185628</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99895809</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99895809</idno>
            <idno type="VID">153675</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A95011)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 153675)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2374:23)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A true copy of a speech made by an English colonel to his regiment, immediately before their late transportation for Flanders at Harwich</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>12 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London? :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1691?]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Caption title.</note>
                  <note>Imprint conjectured from Wing T2633A.</note>
                  <note>Cf. Wing (2nd ed.) T2633A, which is listed as a broadside.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Folger Shakespeare Library, Washington, D.C..</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Great Britain --  Foreign relations --  1689-1702 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  William and Mary, 1689-1702 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="speech">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:153675:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>
               <hi>A true Copy of a Speech made by an</hi> Engliſh <hi>Colonel to his Regiment, immediately before their late Tranſportation for</hi> Flanders <hi>at</hi> Harwich.</head>
            <p>THus far, <hi>Gentlemen</hi> and <hi>Fellow Souldiers,</hi> I have conducted you, in order to your Tranſportation for <hi>Flanders:</hi> The <hi>Honour</hi> of that Poſt which I now enjoy is due only to his Majeſties Good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs; but the <hi>Happineſs</hi> which I propoſe to my ſelf in poſſeſſing it, is a Gift which none but your ſelves can beſtow upon me.</p>
            <p>Your Civil Deportment, and Strict Obedience hitherto, I take as an Earneſt to me of my good Hopes and Succeſſes for the future; and when I conſider'd you are <hi>Engliſh</hi> Men, whoſe <hi>Loyalty</hi> to your <hi>Kings,</hi> and <hi>Natural</hi> Courage, are celebrated and fear'd all <hi>Europe</hi> over; I once thought I might have ſpared both my ſelf and you the trouble of this Meeting. But though long Speeches are now grown out of Date, yet having Something of high Importance to communicate to you, I was reſolved to be rather out of <hi>Faſhion</hi> than out of <hi>Humour</hi> at an old Cuſtom, at <hi>this</hi> time ſo neceſſary for the good of the Nation, and ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice of Our King.</p>
            <p>I muſt acquaint you then, that notwithſtanding our <hi>Loyalty</hi> and <hi>Cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage</hi> may be at as high a pitch as any mortal Men upon Earth can boaſt of; yet the greateſt <hi>Loyalty</hi> may be debaucht, and <hi>Courage</hi> daunted, by the falſe Suggeſtions and malicious Inſinuations of our cunning Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies at home; which, captivating our Underſtandings, and perverting our Judgments, diſarm us more effectually than the Force of our de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared Foes abroad could have done.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Honour</hi> is ſuch an inſeparable Qualification of a <hi>Souldier,</hi> that when the <hi>Honour</hi> is gone the <hi>Souldier</hi> dies, though the <hi>Man</hi> perhaps may drag on miſerably a <hi>deſpiſed</hi> Life. Now the <hi>Juſtice</hi> of the <hi>Cauſe</hi> in which we engage hath ever been eſteemed the <hi>firſt</hi> and greateſt <hi>Motive</hi> to Men of <hi>Honour</hi> to venture their <hi>Lives</hi> and <hi>Fortunes,</hi> to endure all the <hi>Hardſhips</hi> of a tedious War, and to appear <hi>Glorious</hi> with all thoſe <hi>Wounds,</hi> thoſe <hi>Scars,</hi> and <hi>Deformities</hi> upon them, which <hi>ſtill</hi> from the <hi>Juſtice</hi> of the <hi>Cauſe</hi> have been ever reputed <hi>Honourable.</hi> What Man of <hi>Honour</hi> then would appear in a <hi>villanous</hi> Cauſe, and venture his <hi>Limbs</hi> and <hi>Life,</hi> nay,
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:153675:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>and his <hi>Salvation</hi> too, in an unjuſt War? <hi>Slaughter</hi> in <hi>ſuch</hi> becomes <hi>Mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, Plunder</hi> is <hi>Robbery</hi> and <hi>Theft,</hi> and <hi>Victory</hi> it ſelf (if ever it happens to them) oftentimes ends in their <hi>Deſtruction.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Having premiſed theſe things, I muſt now mind you, that proba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly moſt of your ſelves, as well as I, cannot but have obſerved how induſtrious our Enemies at home have been, in repreſenting our <hi>Cauſe</hi> as <hi>unjuſt,</hi> nay, as <hi>Villanous</hi> and <hi>Scandalous</hi> to the Reputation and Name of an <hi>Engliſh</hi> Man, much more of Chriſtian; and, with <hi>Grief</hi> and <hi>Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horrence,</hi> I muſt acknowledge, that the <hi>Generality</hi> of moſt <hi>Towns, Cities,</hi> and <hi>Provinces</hi> too, have of late ſo alter'd their Opinions, and ſo pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lickly aſperſt our <hi>Cauſe,</hi> with injurious terms, not now to be repeated, that I think my ſelf bound in Conſcience to put ſome ſtop to this grow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Miſchief, eſpecially ſince our <hi>Courts</hi> themſelves have not been free from the Contagion, no, not that moſt <hi>Honourable</hi> Court in Parliament aſſembled; in which (to our Grief, and great Amazement) ſome of thoſe <hi>very</hi> Men have appeared the moſt <hi>conſtant Enemies</hi> to our <hi>Cauſe,</hi> who have been reputed Men of the <hi>beſt Eſtates,</hi> and to <hi>this</hi> day lookt upon as the <hi>trueſt Patriots</hi> of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Nation: What then can be leſs expected from me (who have the Honour to command ſuch <hi>brave</hi> Men as you are) than to inſtruct you in thoſe things which may pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve your <hi>Loyalty,</hi> as well as inform and teach you that military Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipline which may animate your <hi>Courage?</hi> Moſt of you have come in <hi>Volunteers</hi> to recruit that Regiment of mine, the greateſt part whereof lye buried in the <hi>Bed</hi> of <hi>Honour.</hi> To you therefore, who have never croſt the Seas, it may be acceptable to know what kind of <hi>Entertain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> and <hi>Reception</hi> you are like to meet with <hi>abroad:</hi> You <hi>Gentlemen,</hi> and <hi>Fellow Soldiers,</hi> who have been Partners of our <hi>Sufferings,</hi> and our repeated <hi>Victories</hi> abroad, will be informed of what hath paſt at <hi>home,</hi> ſince you left your Native Country; and <hi>All</hi> of you will be convinc'd (I hope) how <hi>Juſt</hi> and <hi>Honourable</hi> the <hi>Cauſe</hi> is, in which we are en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaged.</p>
            <p>I ſhall begin at the Fountain and Head of all <hi>Juſtice</hi> and <hi>Honour,</hi> (I mean) the King; and follow the Stream of his moſt <hi>admirable</hi> Quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fications until they are <hi>Loſt</hi> in the Vaſt Ocean of noble Thought. <hi>Firſt</hi> then, he is our <hi>Natural</hi> and <hi>Hereditary</hi> King, and Sovereign Leige Lord, and <hi>We</hi> his <hi>Natural-born</hi> Subjects: Had I no more but <hi>this</hi> to ſay of him, it were more than ſufficient to confirm our bounden Duty and <hi>Loyalty</hi> to him: What can be more <hi>Juſt</hi> and <hi>Honourable</hi> than to obſerve the inviolable Laws of <hi>Nature,</hi> eſpecially when they are inforced by
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:153675:2"/>the poſitive Laws of God? What Man of <hi>Honour</hi> can forbear to Bluſh, or Rage with Indignation, ſhould he hear himſelf accuſed of ſome <hi>un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natural</hi> Sin? The Crimes which we commit againſt <hi>Nature,</hi> make us de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>generate below the Condition of unreaſonable Beaſts, who (even with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Reaſon) preſerve the Law of <hi>Nature:</hi> From the Kid and its Dam to the Lion's Whelp, and the fierceſt Lioneſs, <hi>all</hi> Creatures by <hi>Nature</hi> love and follow thoſe which <hi>nouriſh</hi> and <hi>preſerve</hi> them; and ſhall we, whoſe Profeſſion and Reward is <hi>Honour,</hi> forſake our <hi>Natural</hi> Hereditary King, who is our <hi>Father</hi> and <hi>Protector</hi> too?</p>
            <p>But to proceed: Were he not our King, yet ſince he is ſo, Who doth not wiſh him ſo? <hi>He</hi> it is, who at the hazzard of his own <hi>dear</hi> and <hi>pretious</hi> Life, and at his <hi>own</hi> vaſt Expence, for our ſakes alone, accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted of Three <hi>troubleſome</hi> Crowns, to deliver us from thoſe <hi>two</hi> dreadful Monſters <hi>Popery,</hi> and <hi>Slavery: He</hi> it is, who brought in <hi>Peace</hi> and <hi>Plen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty</hi> among us, and hath <hi>entail'd</hi> them upon us too, beyond the Proſpect of the moſt deſcerning Eye: <hi>He</hi> it is, who ſo tenderly and compaſſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nately Loves us, that he holds our Lives in the <hi>Palms</hi> of his Hands, and is ſo Cautious of expoſing them to the ordinary Dangers of an Enemy, that he heaps up his <hi>own</hi> dear Countrymen as a mighty Bulwark, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore us, whilſt himſelf remains in the Rear, as a ſafe retreat, when dangers overtake us. In his nature he is <hi>Affable, Courtious,</hi> and <hi>Liberal,</hi> event to a <hi>fault:</hi> He is <hi>Merciful,</hi> and ſo free from <hi>Ambition</hi> and <hi>Tyranny</hi> (the Common and darling Vices of Kings) that he hath divided his <hi>Throne</hi> with the <hi>Conſort</hi> of his <hi>Bed,</hi> and hath entruſted his <hi>Power</hi> to the <hi>Will</hi> of his People. But not to dwell too long upon <hi>Words,</hi> let us pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed to <hi>Effects</hi> which are the more <hi>convincing,</hi> by how much they are the more <hi>ſenſible</hi> to us: And,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> How free have we been from the intolerable burden of Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal <hi>Taxes?</hi> How do we wallow in <hi>Wealth,</hi> and <hi>Plenty,</hi> and ſecure even from the <hi>Noiſe</hi> and <hi>Rumour</hi> of <hi>War?</hi> Is not our <hi>Trade</hi> encreaſt, and our <hi>Merchants</hi> freed from the anxious <hi>Fears, Dangers,</hi> and <hi>Loſſes</hi> of the <hi>Seas?</hi> Do not their Numbers daily grow upon us; inſomuch, that <hi>many</hi> of them are neceſſitated to take up with obſcurer Apartments in <hi>private</hi> Corners, for want of larger and freer Houſes in the nobler Streets? Are not the prizes of <hi>Food</hi> and <hi>Rayment,</hi> and all the <hi>neceſſaries</hi> of a Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortable Life, <hi>diminiſhed</hi> to almoſt <hi>one half</hi> of what we paid in former Reigns? Is not <hi>Juſtice</hi> adminiſtred with <hi>Mercy,</hi> is not the <hi>Liberty,</hi> and <hi>Property</hi> of the People, as Sacred to him as his <hi>Prerogative</hi> is, and ought to be to us? Have the <hi>Nobility, Gentry,</hi> or <hi>Comonalty</hi> known, or heard
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:153675:3"/>of any <hi>illegal Impriſonments</hi> or <hi>exceſſive Fines?</hi> Have any <hi>Arch Biſhops,</hi> or <hi>Biſhops</hi> been <hi>turn'd out</hi> of their <hi>Chairs</hi> for <hi>Conſcience ſake,</hi> or <hi>Fellows</hi> of <hi>Colleges</hi> from their <hi>Fellowſhips</hi> and <hi>Properties</hi> by <hi>Mandamus?</hi> Have there been any <hi>Penſioning</hi> or <hi>Bribing</hi> of Parliament Men, and buying the <hi>Miſery</hi> and <hi>Slavery</hi> of the <hi>People</hi> with that <hi>very Mony,</hi> which they themſelves had ſo largely given? Have not the <hi>Votes</hi> in Parl. been as <hi>free</hi> and <hi>unbiaſſed,</hi> as in the bleſſed time of Mr. <hi>Johnſon</hi>'s <hi>quandam Calends</hi> of <hi>May?</hi> Have any <hi>Publik Bills</hi> for the <hi>common Good,</hi> and <hi>impartial Juſtice,</hi> which had paſt <hi>both</hi> Houſes, ever been refus'd, by <hi>this</hi> our <hi>juſt Judge,</hi> and <hi>Father</hi> of his Country? Hath not the <hi>Old Church</hi> of <hi>England</hi> flouriſhed again under him, like a <hi>green Bay Tree,</hi> and her <hi>younger</hi> Sons grown up like <hi>fruitful Vines</hi> about the Houſe of the Lord? And doth it not daily more and more appear how Studious he is to preſerve it? Have the <hi>Spoils</hi> of our <hi>Native</hi> and homeborn Enemies been given to <hi>Foreigners;</hi> or <hi>Honors, Eſtates</hi> and <hi>Employments</hi> beſtowed upon <hi>Strangers?</hi> Are not our <hi>Councils</hi> guided by the <hi>beſt</hi> among the Nobility, in which a Foreigner hath no place, and the <hi>Cabinet</hi> Council by thoſe who moſt <hi>love</hi> and are moſt <hi>be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loved</hi> of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Nation, And approv'd themſelves Men of Honour in former Reigns? Is not the <hi>Trade</hi> and <hi>Engliſh</hi> Intereſt promoted, almoſt to the <hi>ruin</hi> of <hi>Holland,</hi> and are they not ready to <hi>ſink</hi> to their <hi>firſt poor State</hi> for want of <hi>Traffick,</hi> whilſt we ride <hi>Maſters</hi> of the Ocean, and <hi>im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port</hi> to them all <hi>Foreign</hi> Commodities upon <hi>Engliſh</hi> Bottoms, and upon an <hi>Engliſh</hi> account, to the Eternal Glory of our King, and our own vaſt inexhauſtible Profit? Is not the <hi>Gold</hi> and <hi>Silver Coin</hi> of his own Native Country imported hither, to enrich his <hi>Engliſh</hi> Subjects, and not return'd till moſt of it hath paid the Duties of a <hi>Circumciſed Toll?</hi> Are we infeſted with <hi>ſwarms</hi> of <hi>French,</hi> who like <hi>Maw-worms</hi> in our Bowels, eat up the Bread of the poorer Tradeſmen, and ſtarve the hands of our willing and induſtrious Natives? Or have we any reaſon to fear the <hi>French</hi> at <hi>home,</hi> like Wolves, lurking in their Dens? Are our Pallaces guarded by <hi>Frags</hi> in Armour, to the diſhonour of the <hi>Loyal Engliſh</hi> Man? Or our <hi>Engliſh</hi> Armies commanded abroad, by <hi>Hogan Mogan</hi> Generals, who <hi>hate</hi> us? Have we not the preference abroad, both as to <hi>Pay</hi> and <hi>Poſt</hi> of <hi>Honour;</hi> and have not thoſe <hi>ſmall, inconſiderable</hi> Supplies of <hi>Money,</hi> which our Parliaments have preſented to the King, been <hi>firſt</hi> applied to the <hi>conſtant</hi> Pay of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Army? Have we not been always led on to certain <hi>Victory,</hi> by the <hi>Courage</hi> and <hi>Conduct</hi> of our <hi>Invincible</hi> Monarch, and the <hi>Sick</hi> and <hi>Wounded</hi> provided for beyond their Expectations, by his <hi>Care</hi> and <hi>Piety?</hi> Have we not treated the <hi>Priſoners</hi> of our Enemies with an
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:153675:3"/>
               <hi>humanity</hi> becoming the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Nation, whilſt <hi>ours</hi> have <hi>periſhed</hi> among them, by a <hi>barbarity</hi> unexpreſſible? Are we not made <hi>welcome</hi> by the <hi>Dutch</hi> as more than <hi>half</hi> Brothers, and <hi>nouriſhed, ſupported,</hi> and <hi>truſted</hi> by them for <hi>more</hi> than we ſhall <hi>ever</hi> be able to <hi>repay?</hi> Do they not Congra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tulate our <hi>arrival</hi> among them, with all the demonſtrations of wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful <hi>love</hi> and <hi>honour,</hi> and lament our <hi>departure</hi> from them, as if they had believed us their <hi>Guardian Angels?</hi> Are not our <hi>Admirals, Sea Officers, Sea Men,</hi> and our whole <hi>Fleet, honoured, rewarded, paid,</hi> and provided for to that degree, that <hi>Sea Men</hi> abound in every <hi>corner</hi> of the Nation, and have prevented the utmoſt <hi>care</hi> and <hi>diligence</hi> of the <hi>Preſs Maſters?</hi> Are there ſuch Grievances among us, as <hi>vaſt Arrears,</hi> and <hi>Debenters?</hi> Or is there a <hi>Debt</hi> of <hi>Millions</hi> due from the <hi>Crown</hi> to the <hi>Fleet</hi> and <hi>Army,</hi> the <hi>Victuallers, Docks, Shipyards, Tranſport Ships,</hi> &amp;c. to the ruin of many hundred of induſtrious <hi>Engliſh</hi> Families, and the encreaſe and multiply<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of thouſands of <hi>poor neglected Widows</hi> and <hi>Orphans?</hi> But to conclude, (for what Pen, Pencil, or Tongue of Mortal Man, can fully repreſent to you all the <hi>inconceivable</hi> Graces of our illuſtrious Hereditary Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narch) would I compare him with his immediate unfortunate Prede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſor, it would raiſe his Glories to ſo high a pitch, that nothing could blind the Eyes of the whole Univerſe, but by gazing too <hi>ſtedfaſtly</hi> upon his <hi>inſupportable</hi> Luſtre. Compariſons we ſay, are edious, therefore I ſhall forbear giving <hi>that</hi> trouble either to my ſelf or you; yet, leaſt af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter all I have ſaid, any thing material ſhould be neglected, I ſhall <hi>firſt</hi> admoniſh you, after what manner the <hi>Contagion</hi> before mention'd may poſſibly inſinuate it ſelf among us, and then conclude with its certain <hi>Cure</hi> and <hi>Antidote.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Some of our home bred Enemies, in order to render ineffectual what I have here affirmed to you, might probably ſuſpect the <hi>Truth</hi> of what I have here propoſed to you; but till I meet with <hi>that bold</hi> Man, who <hi>dares</hi> deny me the leaſt Article of it, I ſhall deſire <hi>all</hi> of you to take it for <hi>granted,</hi> as I my ſelf do. The <hi>other</hi> ſort of Men are indeed more <hi>ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber,</hi> more <hi>numerous,</hi> and more <hi>conſiderable,</hi> both for <hi>Eſtates</hi> and <hi>Quality;</hi> and theſe, under the ſpecious Pretence of <hi>Compaſſion</hi> for an unfortunate <hi>Exil'd</hi> Prince, endeavour to Extenuate the <hi>Faults,</hi> and magnify the <hi>good Quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties</hi> of the <hi>late</hi> King <hi>James:</hi> They will tell you (it may be) <hi>Firſt,</hi> That he was the <hi>Son</hi> and <hi>Lawful Succeſſor</hi> of our bleſſed King and Martyr <hi>Charles</hi> the Firſt; but <hi>this</hi> can be no Argument in <hi>his</hi> favour, ſince ſome of our Learned <hi>Divines,</hi> even upon the late Anniverſary <hi>Faſt</hi> for his Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyrdom, and before the moſt <hi>Auguſt</hi> Aſſembly of our great City Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nors,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:153675:4"/>have deliver'd from the <hi>Pulpit,</hi> that <hi>Both</hi> might very well deſerve the <hi>Puniſhments</hi> they underwent; and who cannot eaſily <hi>conclude,</hi> that if they <hi>might,</hi> they <hi>did.</hi> They will tell you again, That he was <hi>Merciful</hi> and <hi>Juſt,</hi> a <hi>true born Engliſh</hi> Man, and as <hi>true</hi> a Lover of his Country; That he was a moſt <hi>indulgent</hi> Father to our preſent <hi>Gracious</hi> Queen, and the Princeſs her Siſter; a kind Father in Law, and Unkle, to our pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent <hi>dear</hi> King, and ſo guiltleſs of ever having done him any <hi>Wrong,</hi> that, from his own <hi>Innocency,</hi> he would not be perſwaded his <hi>Nephew</hi> and <hi>Son</hi> would have attempted any thing againſt his <hi>Crown,</hi> or <hi>Perſon;</hi> which (they tell you) prevented him from taking thoſe reaſonable and juſt Meaſures, for his own <hi>Security,</hi> which otherwiſe he <hi>ought,</hi> and <hi>might</hi> have done. Some will ſay, That he was a good <hi>Pay-maſter,</hi> both to his <hi>Creditors</hi> and <hi>Servants,</hi> and to all <hi>poor Tradeſmen;</hi> a very <hi>Father</hi> to his little <hi>Army,</hi> who never wanted their <hi>Pay</hi> during his whole Reign; and ſuch a Lover of a <hi>Sea-man,</hi> that he would even have lived among <hi>them;</hi> with <hi>whom</hi> he had ventur'd his Life, to vindicate the <hi>Honour</hi> and <hi>Intereſt</hi> of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Nation, againſt <hi>theſe very Dutch,</hi> who are now (by the goodneſs of our King) our <hi>intimate, boſom</hi> Friends, and ſomething <hi>more</hi> than Fellow Subjects. They will ſay moreover, That he put no ſuch heavy <hi>Tax maſters</hi> over us, nor oppreſt the poorer Trades with in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tolerable <hi>Exciſe;</hi> nor forc'd us to redeem our <hi>Heads over</hi> and <hi>over</hi> again at a <hi>Price</hi> more valuable to him than the reſt of our whole <hi>Bodies.</hi> That he would never introduce the <hi>French Mode</hi> (which we ſay he always favour'd) of wearing <hi>Sabots,</hi> or wooden Shoes; no, nor the <hi>Dutch</hi> Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhion of <hi>woollen Mittins</hi> inſtead of Gloves, through the exceſſive <hi>Tax</hi> put upon all Sorts of <hi>Leather;</hi> nor yet forbid us the <hi>old Engliſh</hi> uſe of <hi>pou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der'd</hi> Beef, and Pork, by raiſing the Price of our <hi>old Engliſh Salt.</hi> In a word, That he would never have <hi>ſwept</hi> away all our <hi>Engliſh Liberties</hi> and <hi>Properties</hi> at once, with the <hi>Dutch Broom</hi> of a <hi>General Exciſe;</hi> nor our <hi>Native Privileges</hi> and <hi>Birth-rights,</hi> by an <hi>Engliſh</hi> Bill of as <hi>General</hi> a <hi>Natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ralization.</hi> Others will tell you, That he was <hi>Careful</hi> and <hi>Provident,</hi> eſpecially in <hi>refitting</hi> and <hi>augmenting</hi> his <hi>Fleet,</hi> which is the <hi>Honour</hi> and <hi>Security</hi> of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Nation; That he ſtudied the <hi>Honour</hi> and <hi>Intereſt</hi> of <hi>England,</hi> and had he ſtaid till <hi>now</hi> among us, would have ſecur'd to us the <hi>whole uninterrupted Trade</hi> of <hi>Europe;</hi> which the <hi>Dutch foreſaw, fear'd,</hi> and have <hi>prevented;</hi> and, moreover, would have been the <hi>only</hi> Poten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate that could have put a Stop to the exceſſive Power of <hi>France.</hi> That he always promoted an <hi>impartial Liberty</hi> of <hi>Conſcience,</hi> in Matters of <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion,</hi> to thoſe who would live. <hi>Quietly,</hi> and obedient Subjects to the
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:153675:4"/>
               <hi>Civil</hi> Government. This, they ſay, the <hi>Dutch</hi> alſo foreſaw, and the ill Conſequences which it might bring upon <hi>them,</hi> and therefore oppos'd it <hi>underhand</hi> in the Reign of King <hi>Charles</hi> the Second, and turn'd it (a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong other things) to the Ruin of his Brother. They will tell you, he was <hi>eaſy</hi> of <hi>Acceſs,</hi> even to the <hi>meaneſt</hi> of his Subjects, and had a due Regard to his <hi>Nobility;</hi> and they will affirm to you, by many <hi>unde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niable</hi> Teſtimonies (as they pretend) that his <hi>Authority,</hi> and <hi>Preſence</hi> in <hi>Ireland,</hi> chiefly protected the <hi>Proteſtants</hi> there from the Violence of their <hi>Iriſh</hi> Enemies, notwithſtanding a Famous Divine hath written largely to the contrary. But then they proceed to <hi>Juſtify</hi> all they have ſaid, by the <hi>Effects</hi> of that <hi>Cauſe</hi> which they are ſo induſtrious to promote; and then they tell you, That the Nation was never ſo <hi>Rich,</hi> and in ſuch a height of <hi>Proſperity,</hi> as during his Reign: That our <hi>Trade</hi> and our <hi>Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chants</hi> were in a moſt <hi>flouriſhing</hi> Condition: That the <hi>Taxes</hi> were not felt by us, or known to us: That all manner of <hi>Proviſions,</hi> eſpecially <hi>Bread,</hi> were <hi>cheap</hi> and <hi>plentiful:</hi> That the hands of the <hi>poorer Engliſh</hi> Manufacto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers were in <hi>conſtant</hi> Employment: That we had no Apprehenſions or Pretence of <hi>War</hi> whilſt he kept to the <hi>Treaty</hi> of <hi>Nimegen,</hi> as they ſay he did, and was <hi>obliged</hi> to do: That he <hi>really</hi> and <hi>ſincerely</hi> intended and ſtudied the <hi>Good</hi> and <hi>Proſperity</hi> of his People, which nothing ſo much pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vented, as our own unreaſonable <hi>Fears</hi> and <hi>Jealouſies;</hi> and that <hi>thoſe</hi> were maliciouſly <hi>aggravated</hi> and <hi>promoted</hi> by <hi>ſuch</hi> as had reſolved to make themſelves <hi>great</hi> under <hi>this</hi> Government, at the Expence of <hi>his</hi> and <hi>our</hi> Ruin; and a great deal more to this Purpoſe.</p>
            <p>Then they come to the <hi>Crimes</hi> Objected againſt him; and they tell you in <hi>ſhort,</hi> That as to ſome <hi>publick</hi> but <hi>inſignificant</hi> Favours granted to ſome of his own Religion, he was <hi>over-rul'd</hi> in that point, by the <hi>treache<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous</hi> Advice of ſome of his <hi>Protestant Favourites</hi> who <hi>betray'd</hi> him, after they had (by their <hi>own falſe</hi> Councils) firſt expoſed him, and then left him. And as to thoſe <hi>greater</hi> and <hi>villainous</hi> Crimes, which (they tell you) his Soul abhorred; they ſay, That he was moſt <hi>unjustly, irregular<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly</hi> and <hi>impiouſly</hi> Accuſed; and as a Confirmation and ſtrong Argument of this Truth which they affirm, they ſay further, That had he been <hi>Guilty</hi> of any <hi>one</hi> Article, nothing could have been more abſolutely ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary for the <hi>Honour</hi> and <hi>Juſtification</hi> of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Nation, and the <hi>Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verity</hi> of thoſe <hi>very</hi> Perſons who gain'd moſt by this Revolution, than to have proved the <hi>late</hi> King <hi>James Guilty</hi> of <hi>all</hi> or any <hi>one ſingle</hi> Article of <hi>that</hi> Nature objected againſt him, which yet to <hi>this</hi> day they have not been able to do, nor <hi>will</hi> or in truth <hi>can</hi> do, to the Worlds End. And
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:153675:5"/>
               <hi>laſtly,</hi> they conclude with the <hi>Violences</hi> and <hi>Indignities</hi> put upon him; as his <hi>Impriſonment</hi> in his <hi>own</hi> Pallace, and <hi>elſe where</hi> under <hi>Foreign Guards; turning</hi> out of his <hi>own</hi> Pallace, and Royal <hi>Bed</hi> too, at ſuch an unſeaſona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble time, when an <hi>Engliſh</hi> Gentleman would ſcarcely have <hi>diſturb'd</hi> his <hi>Vale de Chambre;</hi> The Execrable <hi>Inſolence</hi> of his <hi>own</hi> Subjects, by <hi>beating</hi> and <hi>ſtriking</hi> at him; and uſing ſuch <hi>Irreverences</hi> towards him, as greater were not offer'd to his Royal Father; and ſuch, as would have been <hi>ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verely</hi> puniſhed under his <hi>good</hi> Government, had they been offer'd by any Engliſh Man to a <hi>Mogan</hi> Foot Man. Many things more they tell of him, which I have not <hi>Patience</hi> to relate; and, in ſhort, they would make him, <hi>falſly appear</hi> what our moſt gracious King <hi>really</hi> and <hi>truly is,</hi> which I am ſo far from believing, that I perſuade my ſelf, there are not <hi>two</hi> Princes in <hi>Europe</hi> more <hi>oppoſite</hi> in <hi>all manner</hi> of Qualifications, than our <hi>preſent</hi> King <hi>William</hi> and the <hi>late</hi> King <hi>James.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now <hi>Gentlemen</hi> and <hi>fellow Soldiers,</hi> you muſt take a great care <hi>not</hi> to believe what I have reported concerning the <hi>late</hi> King <hi>James;</hi> Nay it is abſolutely neceſſary, that you ſhould <hi>obſtinately</hi> disbelieve it all; for it might <hi>poſſibly</hi> make you <hi>Relent,</hi> and inſinuate a certain <hi>Softnefs,</hi> and ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der <hi>Repentance</hi> into your minds, which would, above all things debauch that <hi>Loyalty,</hi> which I would confirm to you. And ſome may ſay, if all this ſhould be true, Why then (beſides many other Violences) do we draw our Swords ſo eagerly againſt that <hi>only</hi> Prince, who is <hi>willing</hi> and <hi>able</hi> to <hi>Protect,</hi> and give <hi>Bread,</hi> to our <hi>Poor, Exil'd, Wronged</hi> Maſter? Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies have Burrows, and Foxes have Holes where to hide their Heads, but our late <hi>poor</hi> King, and the <hi>Son</hi> of a King, Martyr'd for the good of his People, is <hi>ſtill</hi> Perſecuted by his <hi>own Engliſh</hi> Subjects through the Sides of <hi>that</hi> Prince, who hath ſo much Royal <hi>Charity,</hi> and <hi>Generoſity,</hi> as to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tect the <hi>Declining Shipwrack't, Injur'd, Exil'd, Unfortunate Life,</hi> of our <hi>Late, Lawful, Gracious, Engliſh</hi> King.</p>
            <p>But to conclude, if all that hath been ſpoken were unſaid, any, even unthought, yet there remains ſtill <hi>one</hi> Conſideration hitherto untoucht; which of it ſelf is more than ſufficient to elevate your Noble <hi>Courages,</hi> and fix you in the very Center of <hi>Love</hi> and <hi>Loyalty.</hi> In ſhort, we are now (by the Care and Goodneſs of our King) upon the very Brink of entering upon that <hi>Stage</hi> of Glory, where the greateſt Generals and Heroes of the Age are proud to bear a <hi>Part;</hi> we our ſelves ſhall, with them, be Actors in thoſe Famous Tragedies which will for ever be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſented in Hiſtory to the end of all Ages: To us is granted the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſtimable Advantages of being taught and continually practiſing the
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:153675:5"/>military Diſcipline of <hi>Marching, Watching, Faſting,</hi> nay, and <hi>Starving</hi> too, which is the <hi>Perfection</hi> and <hi>Conſummation</hi> of the utmoſt Art of War: To us it is given to divide the rich and heavy <hi>Spoils</hi> of our Enemies, by the means of thoſe <hi>conſtant</hi> Victories to which we have, and (for the ſame Reaſons) ſtill hope to be led on, by the <hi>Courage</hi> and <hi>Conduct</hi> of our Invincible Monarch. But to be ſhort, How much is our Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition preferable to that of the miſerable, neglected <hi>Dutch?</hi> They are <hi>excluded</hi> from thoſe glorious Bleſſings which we <hi>True, Loyal Engliſh</hi> Men enjoy; nay more, They are barrel'd up like Herrings, and ſent as poor and deſpicable Merchandize to every Port of <hi>England,</hi> where they no ſooner Arrive, than they are forc't to take upon them the <hi>Nature</hi> and <hi>Condition</hi> of <hi>Engliſh</hi> Subjects, by which <hi>hard Tenure</hi> they will be obliged to do the <hi>Drudgery</hi> of the Nation, they will be neceſſited to <hi>ſerve</hi> in our <hi>Parliaments,</hi> to be at the ungrateful Expence of <hi>ſerving</hi> the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try as <hi>Sheriffs, Deputy Lieutenants, Juſtices</hi> of the <hi>Peace,</hi> nay, as <hi>Conſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles</hi> and <hi>Church-wardens</hi> too. And what is ſtill an Aggravation of their Hardſhips (which more particularly concerns our ſelves) they will be put even upon doing our own <hi>private</hi> Drudgery; they muſt become <hi>Husbands</hi> to our <hi>Wifes, Fathers</hi> to our <hi>Children, Guardians</hi> to our <hi>Orphans, Stewards</hi> to our <hi>Eſtates, Executors</hi> to our <hi>Wills;</hi> they muſt <hi>cultivate</hi> our <hi>Paſtures,</hi> and <hi>plough up</hi> our <hi>fertile Fields;</hi> they muſt <hi>thraſh</hi> our <hi>Wheat</hi> in our muſty <hi>Barns,</hi> whilſt we are <hi>reaping</hi> ſubſtantial <hi>Honour</hi> in their <hi>Fields</hi> of <hi>Mars.</hi> In a word, they muſt do <hi>all</hi> which we our ſelves ſhould have done, had we been left behind in their <hi>ignoble</hi> Places. All this, and abundantly much more which might be ſaid, will (I hope) fully con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince you, how great is the <hi>Honour, Juſtice, Equity, Piety, Prudence,</hi> and many more innumerable Advantages of our <hi>glorious Cauſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus far, as I ſaid at firſt, <hi>Gentlemen</hi> and <hi>Fellow Companions</hi> at Arms, I have brought you; and if I have detain'd you longer than I intended, remember, That the great Character of our moſt Gracious King, and his <hi>innumerable</hi> good Qualities, have been the occaſion of it. I ſhall now diſmiſs you, until a fair Gale wafts us over to the <hi>Elizian</hi> Fields of <hi>Hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> and <hi>Flanders;</hi> where, probably, moſt of you will put an end to the many Misfortunes of a Soldier's Life.</p>
            <p>When the Colonel had ended his Diſcourſe, a <hi>brisk, gentile</hi> young Fellow, who came early in to the new Recruits, addreſſes himſelf after this manner to his Officer.</p>
            <p>Moſt noble Colonel, your fine Speech has been (I believe) ſo <hi>plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing</hi> to us all, that (for my own part) I rather wiſh you had added
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:153675:6"/>ſomething <hi>more</hi> than left off ſo ſoon; but ſince your Honour hath been pleas'd to take all this Pains for <hi>our Satisfaction,</hi> I beſeech you, in all Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mility, that your Honour will give a poor Souldier leave to mind you of <hi>one Point</hi> which may require a more full and particular Explanation. The Colonel having given a gracious Nod, by way of Conſent, the young Fellow proceeded—I had the Fortune (ſaid he) to be born the younger Son of an <hi>Engliſh</hi> Yeoman, now call'd, forſooth, a Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man: my father had 80 good Pounds, <hi>per Annum;</hi> he kept a good Houſe, and we had <hi>Beef,</hi> and <hi>Pudden,</hi> and <hi>Nogg</hi> good Store. My elder Brother had the good luck to be brought up according to the way of his Anceſtors, that is, to the Plough, and a quiet Country Life; but for my part, my Father, who was now a Gentleman, reſolved that I ſhould be Book learn'd, and ſo I was laſht from School to School un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>til at laſt I become a poor Scholar in the Univerſity of <hi>Cambridge:</hi> But the exceſſive <hi>Taxes, Polls,</hi> and <hi>Prizes</hi> of all Neceſſaries, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> ſince this late Revolution, growing <hi>extreamly</hi> burthenſom to all, and my Father in no Condition upon that ſame Account to allow any thing towards my Subſiſtence, I was forced to beat upon the Hoof to my Father's Houſe. I had not been there long, when I perceiv'd his way of Living ſo alter'd, and our Commons ſo ſhort, that my poor Brains were almoſt turn'd with Grief and Melancholy; and to add to my Afflictions, the Vicar of our Pariſh, who had been an honeſt good Fellow, had ſhut up his Shop, and boarded upon meer <hi>Element</hi> and <hi>Barley Dumplin,</hi> at a poor Farmer's Houſe in the Village. Lord! (noble Colonel) had you ſeen this diſmal Revolution in our Town, it would have broke even your own Courageous Heart; for my part I was not able to bear it any longer, but had fixt my Thoughts upon ſeeking my Fortune. In ſhort, I reſolv'd to <hi>abandon Dwelling,</hi> and (ſaving your Preſence) <hi>out I went a Colonelling.</hi> I had ſoon fixt upon the noble City of <hi>London</hi> for the Center of my hopes. I had not been there long, when my ſmall Stock being almoſt ſpent, I found it abſolntely neceſſary to think of ſome Employ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. I had heard of ſuch as <hi>Knights</hi> of the <hi>Pad,</hi> and ſome of the <hi>Poſt,</hi> which, they ſaid, many Gentlemen (through the Hardneſs of the times) had taken upon them: Or <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> propos'd that I ſhould admit my ſelf into he <hi>Engliſh</hi> or <hi>Dutch</hi> Company of <hi>Clippers</hi> and <hi>Coyners;</hi> but obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving many <hi>hopeful</hi> young Gentlemen of thoſe Profeſſions ſadly conducted (<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> Robbers) up <hi>High Holborn,</hi> it quite baulkt my Fancy to any of thoſe Trades. I reſolved then to ramble into the City, and view the noble Street of <hi>Cheapſide,</hi> intending, if poſſibly I could, to bind
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:153675:6"/>my ſelf Apprentice to ſome honeſt Trade; but when I lookt into their Shops, I found moſt part of the 'Prentices either playing at <hi>Shuttle Cock,</hi> or <hi>aſleep,</hi> or the Shops as <hi>empty</hi> as if viſited only by the Plague. I eaſily invited one or two of them to drink a Pot of Ale, where they told me moſt diſmal Stories of Trade; and, in a word, They ſwore to me, that a Man in <hi>theſe</hi> times had better be a <hi>Hang-man</hi> than a <hi>Trades-man.</hi> I ſoon took leave of my young 'Prentices, and reſolv'd to view the <hi>remoter</hi> Parts of the City, thinking with my ſelf, That poſſibly the Calamity might not have ſpread ſo far. I found my ſelf at laſt about <hi>Spittle Fields;</hi> but noble Colonel, had your Honour ſeen the poor <hi>Engliſh Weavers, Button-makers,</hi> &amp;c. ſitting at their Doors all along the Streets, with their <hi>Heads</hi> in their <hi>Hands,</hi> whilſt their <hi>Wives</hi> were <hi>curſing</hi> the <hi>French</hi> Dogs, (as they call'd them) who had taken the Bread out of their Childrens Mouths, for which they were ſadly Bawling; had you heard them <hi>blaſpheme</hi> the Government; or had your Honour's delicate Noſe ſmelt the ſtrong Smell of <hi>Garlick, Onions,</hi> and <hi>Cabbage,</hi> which abounded, your Honour would have thought your ſelf rather in ſome Common Shore than in the famous City of <hi>London</hi> I ſoon took my leave of this ſad Country, and ſeeing no hopes of Employment at <hi>Land,</hi> I reſolv'd to try my Fortune at <hi>Sea;</hi> to that purpoſe I travell'd down to <hi>Wapping,</hi> hoping to meet with ſome honeſt Maſter that might entertain me; but (would you believe it) the Sea-men had <hi>fled</hi> with as much diligence from thence, as I had taken care to get thither; ſo that I ſcarce found any body, beſides whole <hi>Shoals</hi> of Sea mens <hi>Widows</hi> and <hi>Wives,</hi> with their <hi>Children</hi> and <hi>Orphans,</hi> all bitterly curſing <hi>Preſs-maſters,</hi> the <hi>Navy Office,</hi> &amp;c. nor did they ſpare <hi>Whitehall,</hi> or <hi>Kenſington.</hi> I was ſoon weary of <hi>this Place</hi> alſo, which I lookt upon as a Repreſentation of Hell it ſelf, for I found nothing but <hi>weeping,</hi> and <hi>wailing,</hi> and <hi>gnaſhing</hi> of <hi>Teeth:</hi> Back then I return'd to <hi>Holborn,</hi> where hearing the Noiſe of a Drum, and ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Majeſty of a Sergeant, and his Halbard marching before it, and obſerving the Huzza's of <hi>three</hi> or <hi>four Children</hi> at the end of [<hi>God ſave King</hi> W. <hi>and Queen</hi> M.] I was ſo animated at this time that I reſolved imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately (right or wrong) to Liſt my ſelf a <hi>Souldier.</hi> I enquir'd after the Colonel, which I found to be your Honour; and hearing all People give you a good word, I was preſently entertain'd, and here I am at your Service. I have troubled you with all this, noble Colonel, only to ſhew you, That it was <hi>Neceſſity</hi> which brought me hither; I neither regard the <hi>Juſtice</hi> nor <hi>Injuſtice</hi> of the Cauſe; I neither fight for King <hi>W.</hi> nor againſt King <hi>J.</hi> but I <hi>venture</hi> my Life to <hi>preſerve</hi> my Life by <hi>Bread</hi> and
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:153675:7" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <hi>Pay.</hi> Your Honour is ſenſible that a young Man's Life is valued at Seven years Purchaſe; and to venture <hi>Seven years</hi> Purchaſe againſt <hi>Nothing,</hi> is ſuch a Bargain as the Devil himſelf would be aſhamed to accept. Now if we want our <hi>Pay,</hi> we want <hi>all Things,</hi> and by conſequence have <hi>Nothing,</hi> which I hope will never be our ſad Caſe. And now (moſt noble Colonel) I only beg the Liberty of one word more. Since I was admitted into this Honourable Employment, I have kept Company with many of my own Profeſſion; ſome ſerv'd in <hi>Flanders</hi> un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the D. of <hi>Monmouth,</hi> and theſe unanimouſly applaud the <hi>good Uſage,</hi> and the <hi>Pay</hi> they received in that Service; I have converſt with others who ſerv'd under the late King <hi>J.</hi> and when I enquire of them, how they were treated and paid in thoſe days, they fall a <hi>ſighing</hi> and <hi>ſobbing,</hi> as if their Hearts would break, and I can ſcarce get any thing from them, but, <hi>ah, ſhall we never ſee thoſe days again?</hi> And ſuch Raptures of <hi>Grief</hi> and <hi>Love</hi> for his Memory, that they almoſt amazed me. But truly, noble Colonel, when I diſcourſe with thoſe who have made theſe <hi>late</hi> Cam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paigns in <hi>Flanders,</hi> all of them <hi>univerſally</hi> (except thoſe in your Honours Regiment) have given us a Relation ſo <hi>contrary</hi> in all Particulars to thoſe of the <hi>former</hi> Reigns, and eſpecially, as to the main points of <hi>Pay</hi> and <hi>good Uſage,</hi> that, if your Honour will vouchſafe to give us a Satisfactory word or two, particularly to thoſe two points (which I can aſſure you are the great Motives and Concern of us all) your Honour may be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fident that we will follow you through <hi>Fire</hi> as well as <hi>Water,</hi> even to the <hi>Gates</hi> of <hi>Paris,</hi> if you command us. The young Fellow having made a low obeiſance, the Colonel ſmiling, thus replied. Young Man, I have heard your long Speech with <hi>Patience,</hi> and forgive many <hi>Impertinences</hi> in it. But that nothing may be wanting to your <hi>entire</hi> Satisfaction, take this in anſwer to the two <hi>main Points</hi> you ſpeak off. <hi>Firſt,</hi> Gentlemen, I do ſolemly promiſe that your Uſage in <hi>Flanders</hi> ſhall always be <hi>worthy</hi> of <hi>Engliſh</hi> Men, and the <hi>Goodneſs</hi> and <hi>Juſtice</hi> of our Cauſe; and next, as to your <hi>Pay,</hi> I do here plight my <hi>Troth,</hi> and my dear <hi>Honour,</hi> which I value above my Life, that you ſhall be all of you <hi>conſtantly, certainly,</hi> and <hi>ſoundly</hi> Paid before you come back. In the mean time return to your Quarters till further Orders. Having ſaid this, he mounted Pad, and took the freſh Air.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
